Zach Kaplan: Keith and I lead a research team.
زاك كابلان: نقود أنا وكيث فريق بحث علمي.
We investigate materials and technologies
نقوم باستقصاء المواد والتقانات
that have unexpected properties. Over the last three years,
التي لديها خواص غير متوقعة. خلال السنوات الثلاث الأخيرة،
we found over 200 of these things, and so we looked
وجدنا أكثر من 200 منها، وهكذا نظرنا
back into our library and selected six we thought would be most
إلى مكتبتنا واخترنا ستة اعتقدنا أنها ستكون أكثر
surprising for TED.
إدهاشا لمؤتمر تيد "TED".
Of these six, the first one that we're going to talk about
من هذه الستة، الأولى التي سنتحدث عنها
is in the black envelope you're holding.
هي في الملف الأسود التي تحملونه.
It comes from a company in Japan called GelTech. Now go ahead and open it up.
وقد جاءت من شركة في اليابان تسمى GelTech. الآن قوموا بفتحه.
Keith Schacht: Now be sure and take the two pieces apart.
كيث شاخت: الآن تأكدوا من أخذ القطعتين منفصلتين.
What's unexpected about this is that it's soft, but it's also a strong magnet.
الشيء الغير متوقع بخصوص هذا هو أنه لين، لكنه كذلك مغناطيس قوي.
Zach and I have always been fascinated
أنا وزاك كنا دائما مبهورين
observing unexpected things like this.
بمشاهدة الأمور الغير متوقعة كهذه.
We spent a long time thinking about why this is, and it's just recently that we realized:
قضينا وقتا طويلا نفكر لماذا هذا، ومؤخرا فقط أدركنا أنه:
it's when we see something unexpected,
حين ترى شيئا غير متوقع،
it changes our understanding of the way things work.
فإنه يغير فهمنا لطريقة عمل الأشياء.
As you're seeing this gel magnet for the first time,
وكما ترون هذا الهلام المغناطيسي لأول مرة،
if you assume that all magnets had to be hard,
إن افترضتم أن كل المغناطيسات صلبة،
then seeing this surprised you and it changed your understanding
حينها رؤية هذا تفاجئكم وتغير فهمكم
of the way magnets could work.
للطريقة التي قد تشتغل بها المغناطيسات.
ZK: Now, it's important to understand what the unexpected properties are.
ز.ك: الآن، من المهم فهم ما هي الخصائص الغير متوقعة.
But to really think about the implications of what this makes possible,
لكن أن تفكر بالفعل حول الآثار التي يجعلها هذا ممكنة،
we found that it helps to think about how it could be applied in the world.
وجدنا أنه يساعد في التفكير حول كيف يمكن أن يتم تطبيقه في العالم.
So, a first idea is to use it on cabinet doors.
وهكذا، أول فكرة هي استعماله في أبواب الخزانة.
If you line the sides of the cabinets using the gel material --
إذا نظمتم جوانب الخزانات باستعمال الهلام المغناطيسي،
if a cabinet slams shut it wouldn't make a loud noise,
حين تغلق الخزانة بعنف لن تصدر صوتا عاليا،
and in addition the magnets would draw the cabinets closed.
وبالإضافة إلى أن المغناطيس ستبقي الخزانة مغلقة.
Imagine taking the same material, but putting it on the bottom of a sneaker.
تخيلوا أخذ نفس المادة، ووضعها في أسفل حذاء رياضة.
You know, this way you could go to the container store and buy one of those
تعلمون، بهذه الطريقة يمكنكم أن تذهبوا إلى المحل وتشتروا إحدى تلك
metal sheets that they hang on the back of your door, in your closet,
الصفائح المعدنية التي تعلق خلف الباب في خزانتكم
and you could literally stick your shoes up instead of using a shelf.
ويمكنكم حرفيا لصق أحذيتكم بدل استعمال الرفوف.
For me, I really love this idea.
وبالنسبة لي، فعلا أحب هذه الفكرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If you come to my apartment and see my closet,
إن أتيتم إلى شقتي ورأيتم خزانتي،
I'm sure you'd figure out why: it's a mess.
أنا متأكد من أنكم ستعرفون لماذا. إنها فوضى.
KS: Seeing the unexpected properties and then seeing a couple of
ك.ش: رؤية الخصائص الغير متوقعة ثم رؤية البعض من
applications -- it helps you see why this is significant, what the potential is.
التطبيقات، تساعدكم على فهم لماذا هو مهم، نوعا ما ما هي الإمكانيات.
But we've found that the way we present our ideas
لكننا وجدنا أنه الطريقة التي نعرض بها أفكارنا،
it makes a big difference.
تصنع فارقا كبيرا.
ZK: It was like six months ago that Keith and I were out in L.A.,
ز.ك: منذ حوالي ستة أشهر كنت مع كيث في لوس أنجلس،
and we were at Starbucks having coffee with Roman Coppola.
وكنا في ستاربكس نشرب قهوة مع رومان كوبولا.
He works on mostly music videos and commercials
يشتغل غالبا في الفيديوهات الموسيقية والإعلانات التجارية
with his company, The Directors Bureau.
مع شركته، مكتب المديرين.
As we were talking, Roman told us that he's kind of an inventor on the side.
لكن، ونحن نتحدث، أخبرنا رومان أنه من جهته مخترع نوعا ما.
And we were showing him the same
وكنا نريه نفس
gel magnet that you're holding in your hand -- and you know,
الهلام المغناطيسي الذي تحملونه في يدكم وتعلمون،
we shared the same ideas. And you could see it in his face:
تشاركنا في نفس الأفكار. ويمكنكم رؤية ذلك على وجهه.
Roman starts to get really excited and he whips out this manila folder;
بدأ رومان يتحمس وخطف ملف المانيلا.
he opens it up and Keith and I look in,
فتحه ونظرت أنا وكيث بداخله،
and he starts showing us concepts that he's been working on.
وبدأ يرينا الأفكار التي كان يشتغل عليها.
These things just get him really excited. And so we're looking
هذه الأشياء جعلته بالفعل متحمسا. وهكذا كنا ننظر
at these concepts, and we were just like, whoa, this guy's good.
إلى تلك الأفكار، وكنا نفكر، واو، هذا الشخص جيد.
Because the way that he presented the concept -- his approach
لأن الطريقة التي عرض بها أفكاره، ومقاربته
was totally different than ours. He sold it to you as if it was for sale right now.
كانت مختلفة تماما عن طريقتنا. لقد باعكم إياها وكأنها متوفرة للبيع حاليا.
When we were going in the car back to the airport,
وحين كنا في السيارة عائدين إلى المطار،
we were thinking: why was this so powerful?
كنا نفكر، لماذا ذلك كان جبارا جدا؟
And as we thought about it more, we realized that
ونحن نفكر في الأمر أدركنا
it let you fill in all the details about the experience,
أنه يجعلك تتشبع بمعلومات عن التجربة،
just as if you saw it on TV. So, for TED we decided to take our favorite
وكأنك رأيتها على التلفاز. وبالتالي، من أجل تيد قررنا اخذ أفكارنا المفضلة
idea for the gel magnet and work with Roman and his team
للهلام المغناطيسي والعمل مع رومان وفريقه
at the Directors Bureau to create a commercial for a product
في مكتب المديرين لإنشاء إعلان تجاري لمنتوج
from the future.
من المستقبل.
Narrator: Do you have a need for speed?
(فيديو): هل ليدكم رغبة في السرعة؟
Inventables Water Adventures dares you to launch yourself
مغامرات الماء المخترعة تتحداكم لإطلاق أنفسكم
on a magnetically-levitating board down a waterslide
على لوح مرفوع-مغناطيسيا نزولا في المنزلق المائي
so fast, so tall, that when you hit the bottom, it uses brakes to stop.
سريع وشاهق بحيث أنه حين ترتطمون بالأسفل، يستعمل فرامل للتوقف.
Aqua Rocket: coming this summer.
صاروخ أكوا. يأتيكم هذا الصيف.
KS: Now, we showed the concept to a few people before this,
ك.ش: الآن، أرينا التصور لبعض الأشخاص قبل هذا،
and they asked us, when's it coming out?
وسألونا، متى سيصدر؟
So I just wanted to let you know, it's not actually coming out,
لذلك أردت فقط أن أعلمكم، أنه لن يصدر بالفعل،
just the concept is.
فقط التصور.
ZK: So now, when we dream up these concepts, it's important for us
ز.ك: وهكذا الآن، حين نحلم بهذه التصورات، من المهم لنا
to make sure that they work from a technical standpoint.
أن نكون متأكدين أنها تشتغل من وجهة نظر تقنية.
So I just want to quickly explain how this would work.
إذن أريد فقط أن أشرح بعجالة كيف قد يشتغل هذا.
This is the magnetically-levitating board that they mentioned in the commercial.
هذا هو اللوح المرفوع-مغناطيسيا الذي ذكر في الإعلان التجاري.
The gel that you're holding would be lining the bottom of the board.
الهلام الذي تمسكونه سيرتب أسفل اللوح.
Now this is important for two reasons.
الآن هذا مهم لسببين.
One: the soft properties of the magnet that make it so that, if it were
الأول، الخصائص الناعمة للمغناطيس والتي تجعله التي تجعله كذلك إن حصل و
to hit the rider in the head, it wouldn't injure him.
ضربت الراكب في رأسه، لن تتسبب في إصابته.
In addition, you can see from the diagram on the right,
بالإضافة إلى ذلك، يمكنكم الرؤية من خلال الرسم البياني على اليمين،
the underpart of the slide would be an electromagnet.
الجزء السفلي للوح سيكون كهرومغنطيسيا.
So this would actually repel the rider a little bit as you're going down.
حيث هذا يمكن أن يقوم بصد الراكب قليلا وهو يسير نحو الأسفل.
The force of the water rushing down, in addition to that repulsion force,
قوة اندفاع الماء نحو الأسفل، بالإضافة إلى قوة التنافر،
would make this slide go faster than any slide on the market.
ستجعل المزلجة تسير أسرع من أي مزلجة في السوق.
It's because of this that you need the magnetic braking system.
وبسبب ذلك تحتاجون نظام الفرملة.
When you get to the very bottom of the slide --
حين تصلون إلى أسفل المزلجة --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
-- the rider passes through an aluminum tube.
-- الراكب يمر عبر أنبوب ألمنيوم.
And I'm going to kick it to Keith to explain why that's important
وسأمرر الكرة إلى كيث ليشرح لماذا ذلك مهم
from a technical standpoint.
من وجهة نظر تقنية.
KS: So I'm sure all you engineers know that even though aluminum is
ك.ش: إذن أنا متأكد أن المهندسين منكم يعرفون أنه وبالرغم من أن الألمنيوم
a metal, it's not a magnetic material. But something unexpected
معدن، فإنه ليس بمادة مغناطيسية. لكن أمرا غير متوقع
happens when you drop a magnet down an aluminum tube.
يحدث حين ترمي مغناطيسا نزولا في أنبوب ألمنيوم.
So we set up a quick experiment here to show that to you.
إذن قمنا بإعداد تجربة سريعة هنا لنريكم ذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, you see the magnet fell really slowly.
الآن، ترون المغناطيس يسقط فعلا ببطء.
Now, I'm not going to get into the physics of it,
الآن، لن أتطرق إلى فيزياء الأمر،
but all you need to know is that the faster the magnet's falling,
لكن كل ما تحتاجون لمعرفته هو أنه بقدر سرعة هبوط المغناطيس،
the greater the stopping force.
بقدر عظمة قوة الإيقاف.
ZK: Now, our next technology is actually a 10-foot pole,
ز.ك: الآن، تقنيتنا التالية هي بالفعل عصا طولها 10 أقدام،
and I have it right here in my pocket.
وها هي هنا في جيبي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
There're a few different versions of it.
هناك بضعة اصدارات مختلفة منها.
KS: Some of them automatically unroll like this one.
ك.ش: بعضها ينشر تلقائيا مثل هذه.
They can be made to automatically roll up, or they can be made
يمكن أن تجعل تلقائية اللف، أو يمكن أن تجعل
stable, like Zach's, to hold any position in between.
ثابتة، كما التي عند زاك، لتحافظ على أي وضعية بينية.
ZK: As we were talking to the vendor -- to try to learn about
ز.ك: إذن الآن، ونحن نتحدث للمصنع لنحاول التعرف على
how you could apply these, or how they're being applied currently --
كيف يمكن أن نصنع هذه أو كيف يتم تطبيقها حاليا،
he was telling us that, in the military they use this one
كان يخبرنا أنه في الجيش يستعملون هذه
so soldiers can keep it on their chests -- very concealed --
بحيث يمكن للجنود إخفاؤها في صدرياتهم،
and then, when they're out on the field, erect it as an antenna
وثم حين يكونون في الميدان، نصبها كهوائي
to clearly send signals back to the base.
لإرسال رسائل بوضوح للقاعدة.
In our brainstorms, we came up with the idea you could use it for a soccer goal:
في عمليات العصف الذهني التي قمنا بها، خرجنا بفكرة يمكن استعمالها في مرمى كرة القدم،
so at the end of the game, you just roll up the goal and put it in your gym bag.
بحيث في نهاية المباراة، تقومون فقط بلف المرمى ووضعه في حقيبتكم الرياضية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
KS: Now, the interesting thing about this is,
ك.ش: الآن، الأمر المثير للإهتمام بهذا الخصوص هو،
you don't have to be an engineer to appreciate why
ليس عليك أن تكون مهندسا لتقدر لماذا
a 10-foot pole that can fit in your pocket is so interesting.
عصا طولها 10 أقدام يمكن وضعها في جيبك هي أمر مثير للإهتمام.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So we decided to go out onto the streets of Chicago
إذن قررنا أن نخرج إلى شوارع شيكاغو
and ask a few people on the streets what they thought you could do with this.
وسؤال بعض الناس في الشارع حول ما يظنون أنه بإمكانهم القيام به بهذه.
Man: I clean my ceiling fans with that and I get the spider webs
(فيديو): سأنظف بها مروحة السقف، وأزيل شبكات العنكبوت
off my house -- I do it that way.
من منزلي، سأستخدمها بتلك الطريقة.
Woman: I'd make my very own walking stick.
سأصنع عصا المشي الخاصة بي.
Woman: I would create a ladder to use to get up on top of the tree.
سأقوم بإنشاء سلم أستعمله للوصول إلى أعلى الشجرة.
Woman: An olive server.
خادم زيتون.
Man: Some type of extension pole -- like what the painters use.
أحد أنواع العصا الممتدة، مثل التي يستخدمها الرسامون.
Woman: I would make a spear that, when you went deep sea diving,
سأصنع رمحا بحيث حين تذهب للغطس عميقا في البحر،
you could catch the fish really fast, and then roll it back up,
تستطيع أن تمسك السمك بسرعة فعلا وتلفها مجددا
and you could swim easier ... Yeah.
ويمكنك أن تسبح بشكل أسهل، نعم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
ZK: Now, for our next technology we're going to do a little demonstration,
ز.ك: الآن بخصوص تقانتنا التالية سنقوم ببعض الإستعراض،
and so we need a volunteer from the audience.
ولذلك نحتاج متطوعا من الجمهور.
You sir, come on up.
أنت سيدي، تعال هنا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Come on up. Tell everybody your name.
تعال هنا. أخبر الجميع باسمك.
Steve Jurvetson: Steve.
ستيف جيرفيتسون.
ZK: It's Steve. All right Steve, now, follow me.
ز.ك: إنه ستيف. حسنا ستيف، الآن اتبعني.
We need you to stand right in front of the TED sign.
نريد منك أن تقف مباشرة أمام علامة تيد.
Right there. That's great.
هناك تماما. ممتاز.
And hold onto this. Good luck to you.
وأمسك هذه. حظا موفقا لك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
KS: No, not yet.
ك.ش: لا، ليس بعد.
ZK: I'd just like to let you all know that this presentation
ز.ك: أريد فقط أن أعلمكم أن هذا العرض
has been brought to you by Target.
قدم لكم من طرف Target.
KS: Little bit -- that's perfect, just perfect.
ك.ش: قليلا فقط -- ممتاز، ممتاز.
Now, Zach, we're going to demonstrate
الآن، زاك، سنقوم باستعراض
a water gun fight from the future.
معركة مسدس مائي من المستقبل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So here, come on up to the front. All right, so
إذن هنا، تعال إلى هنا. حسنا، إذن
now if you'll see here -- no, no, it's OK.
الآن إن نظرت هنا -- لا، لا، لا بأس.
So, describe to the audience the temperature of your shirt. Go ahead.
إذن، صف للجمهور درجة حرارة قميصك. تفضل.
SJ: It's cold.
س.ج: إنه بارد.
KS: Now the reason it's cold is that's it's not actually water loaded
ك.ش: الآن سبب برودته هو أنه في الواقع ليس مبتلا بالماء
into these squirt guns -- it's a dry liquid developed by 3M.
برشاش هذه المسدسات. إنه سائل جاف طور من قبل 3M.
It's perfectly clear, it's odorless, it's colorless.
إنه واضح بشكل تماما، ليس له رائحة، ليس له لون.
It's so safe you could drink this stuff.
إنه آمن جدا إلى درجة أنه يمكنكم شربه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And the reason it feels cold is because it evaporates
والسبب الذي يجعله باردا هو أنه يتبخر
25 times faster than water.
25 مرة أسرع من الماء.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
All right, well thanks for coming up.
حسنا، شكرا على قدومك.
ZK: Wait, wait, Steven -- before you go we filled this with the dry liquid
ز.ك: انتظر، انتظر، ستيفن -- قبل أن تذهب قمنا بتعبئة هذا بالسائل الجاف
so during the break you can shoot your friends.
حتى يمكنك أن تطلق على أصدقائك خلال فترة الإستراحة.
SJ: Excellent, thank you.
س.ج: ممتاز، شكرا لك.
KS: Thanks for coming up. Let's give him a big round of applause.
ك.ش: شكرا على قدومك. لنصفق له.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So what's the significance of this dry liquid?
إذن ما أهمية هذا السائل الجاف؟
Early versions of the fluid were actually used on a Cray Supercomputer.
النسخ الأولى من السائل قد استعملت في الواقع على حاسوب كراي الخارق (Cray).
Now, the unexpected thing about this
الآن، الأمر الغير متوقع بخصوص هذا
is that Zach could stand up on stage and drench
هو أن زاك يمكنه أن يقف في المنصة ويبلل
a perfectly innocent member of the audience without any concern
شخصا بريئا تماما من الجمهور دون أي قلق
that we'd damage the electronics, that we'd get him wet,
من أن يتلف الإلكترونيات، أن يجعله مبتلا،
that we'd hurt the books or the computers. It works because it's non-conductive.
أن يؤذي ذلك الكتب أو الحواسيب. يشتغل لأنه ليس موصلا.
So you can see here, you can immerse a whole circuit board
وبالتالي يمكنكم أن تروا هنا، يمكنكم غمر لوحة دارة كاملة
in this and it wouldn't cause any damage.
في هذا ولن يتم إتلافها.
You can circulate it to draw the heat away.
يمكنكم نشرها لإبعاد الحرارة.
But today it's most widely used in office buildings --
لكن اليوم يستخدم بكثرة في مباني المكاتب --
in the sprinkler system -- as a fire-suppression fluid.
في نظام مطفئة الحرائق كسائل لإخماد النار.
Again, it's perfectly safe for people. It puts out the fires, doesn't hurt anything.
مجددا، إنه آمن تماما للناس. يقضي على الحرائق، ولا يؤذي شيئا.
But our favorite idea for this
لكن فكرتنا المفضلة من كل هذا
was using it in a basketball game. So during halftime,
هي استخدامه في لعبة كرة السلة. بحيث في الإستراحة،
it could rain down on the players, cool everyone down,
يمكن أن يرش على اللاعبين، يبرد الجميع،
and in a matter of minutes it would dry. Wouldn't hurt the court.
وفي غضون دقائق سيجف. لن يؤذي الملعب.
ZK: Our next technology comes to us from a company in Japan
ز.ك: التقانة التالية تأتي من شركة في اليابان
called Sekisui Chemical. One of their R&amp;D engineers
تدعى Sekisui Chemical، أحد مهندسي البحث والتطوير عندهم
was working on a way to make plastic stiffer.
كان يشتغل حول طريقة لجعل البلاستيك أكثر صلابة.
While he was doing this, he noticed an unexpected thing.
وأثناء ذلك، لاحظ أمرا غير متوقع.
We have a video to show you.
عندنا فيديو سنريكم إياه.
KS: So you see there, it didn't bounce back. Now, this was
ك.ش: إذن ترون هنا، لم يرتد رجوعا. الآن، هذا كان
an unintended side effect of some experiments they were doing.
مفعولا جانبيا غير مقصود من بعض التجارب التي كانوا يقومون بها.
It's technically called, "shape-retaining property."
تسمى تقنيا، "خاصية الإحتفاظ بالشكل."
Now, think about your interactions with aluminum foil.
الآن، فكروا حول التفاعلات مع رقاقات الألومنيوم.
Shape-retaining is common in metal: you bend a piece of aluminum foil,
الإحتفاظ بالشكل أمر معتاد في المعادن. تقوم بلي رقاقة ألمنيوم،
and it holds its place. Contrast that with
وتحافظ على موضعها. وقارنوا ذلك مع،
a plastic garbage can -- and you can push in the sides
شيء مثل، سلة مهملات بلاستيكية، ويمكنكم أن تضغطوا الجوانب
and it always bounces back.
وستعود دائما إلى الإرتداد.
ZK: For example, you could make a watch that wraps around your wrist,
ز.ك: على سبيل المثال، يمكنكم صنع ساعة يدوية تلتف حول رسغكم
but doesn't use a buckle.
دون استعمال مشبك.
Taking it a little further, if you wove
بأخذ الأمر أبعد قليلا، إن قمتم بنسج
those strips together -- kind of like a little basket -- you could make
تلك الأشرطة مع بعضها البعض، مثل سلة صغيرة نوعا ما، يمكنكم صنع
a shape-retaining sheet, and then you could embed it in a cloth:
غطاء محافظ على الشكل، ثم يمكنكم تضمينه في قماش
so you could make a picnic sheet that wraps around the table,
بحيث يمكنكم صنع غطاء طاولة نزهة يلتف حول الطاولة،
so that way on a windy day it wouldn't blow away.
وبالتالي في يوم عاصف لن يطير بعيدا.
For our next technology, it's hard to observe
فيما يتعلق بالتقانة الموالية، من الصعب ملاحظة
the unexpected property by itself, because it's an ink.
الخواص الغير متوقعة ذاتها لإنه حبر.
So, we've prepared a video to show it applied to paper.
إذن، قمنا بتحضير فيديو لنريكم تطبيقها على الورق.
KS: As this paper is bending, the resistance of the ink changes.
ك.ش: كلما طويت الورقة، تتغير مقاومة الحبر.
So with simple electronics, you can detect how much the page is being bent.
إذن وباستعمال إلكترونيات بسيطة، يمكنكم كشف عدد الصفحات المطوية.
Now, to think about the potential for this,
الآن فكروا في الإمكانيات التي يتيحها هذا،
think of all the places ink is supplied: on business cards,
فكروا في كل الأماكن التي فيها حبر. في بطاقات الأعمال،
on the back of cereal boxes, board games. Any place you use ink,
خلف علبة حبوب الفطور، ألعاب اللوح. أي مكان يستخدم فيه الحبر
you could change the way you interact with it.
يمكنكم أن تغيروا الطريقة التي تتفاعلون بها معه.
ZK: So my favorite idea for this is to apply the ink to a book.
ز.ك: إذن الفكرة المفضلة لدي هي تطبيق هذا الحبر في كتاب.
This could totally change the way that you interface with paper.
في مقدور هذا أن يغير تماما الطريقة التي نتعامل بها مع الورق.
You see the dark line on the side and the top. As you turn the pages
ترون الخط الغامق في الجانب والأعلى. كلما قلبتم الصفحات
of the book, the book can actually detect what page you're on,
في الكتاب، يمكن للكتاب بالفعل معرفة الصفحة التي توجدون فيها
based on the curvature of the pages.
بناء على تقويس الصفحات.
In addition, if you were to fold in one of the corners, then you could program
بالإضافة إلى ذلك، إن قمتم بطي إحدى الأطراف، آنذاك يمكنكم برمجة
the book to actually email you the text on the page for your notes.
الكتاب ليرسل لكم بريدا إلكترونيا بالنص الموجود في تلك الصفحة.
KS: For our last technology, we worked again with Roman and his team
ك.ش: وبخصوص آخر التقانات لدينا، اشتغلنا مجددا مع رومان وفريقه
at the Directors Bureau to develop a commercial from the future
في مكتب المديرين لتطوير إعلان تجاري من المستقبل
to explain how it works.
لنرى كيف يعمل.
Old Milk Carton: Oh yeah, it smells good.
(فيديو): أوه نعم، رائحة جيدة.
Who are you?
من أنت؟
New Milk Carton: I'm New Milk.
أنا حليب جديد.
OMC: I used to smell like you.
كانت رائحتي مثلك قبلا.
Narrator: Fresh Watch, from Inventables Dairy Farms.
Freshwatch من مزارع ألبان Inventables.
Packaging that changes color when your milk's gone off.
التعليب الذي يغير لونه حين يفسد حليبكم.
Don't let milk spoil your morning.
لا تدع الحليب يفسد صباحك.
ZK: Now, this technology was developed by these two guys:
ز.ك: الآن، هذه التكنولوجيا تم تطويرها من طرف هذين الشخصين --
Professor Ken Suslick and Neil Rakow, of the University of Illinois.
البروفيسور كين سوسليك ونيل راكو من جامعة إلينوي.
KS: Now the way it works: there's a matrix of color dyes.
ك.ش: الآن الطريقة التي تشتغل بها: هناك مصفوفة من الأصباغ الملونة.
And these dyes change color in response to odors.
وهذه الأصباغ تغير لونها تجاوبا مع الروائح.
So the smell of vanilla, that might change the four on the left to brown
وبالتالي رائحة الفانيلا، التي قد تغير الرابع على اليسار البني
and the one on the right to yellow. This matrix can produce
والذي على اليسار أصفر، بحيث يمكن لهذه المصفوفة إنتاج
thousands of different color combinations to represent thousands of different smells.
الآلاف من تركيبات الألوان لتمثيل آلاف الروائح المختلفة.
But like in the milk commercial, if you know what odor you want to detect,
لكن كما في الإعلان التجاري للحليب، إن كنت تعرف أي رائحة تريد الكشف عنها،
then they can formulate a specific dye to detect just that odor.
آنذاك يمكنك صياغة صباغة محددة للكشف عن تلك الرائحة.
ZK: Right. It was that that started a conversation with Professor Suslick and myself,
ز.ك: صحيح. كان ذلك ما بدأ محادثة بيني وبين البروفيسور سوسليك،
and he was explaining to me the things that this is making possible,
وقد كان يشرح لي أن الأمور التي يجعلها ذلك ممكنة.
beyond just detecting spoiled food. It's really where the significance of it lies.
غير فقط الكشف عن الطعام الفاسد هي بالفعل مكمن أهميته.
His company actually did a survey of firemen all across the country to try to learn,
شركته في الواقع قد أجرت استطلاعا على رجال الإطفاء في أرجاء الدولة لمحاولة فهم،
how are they currently testing the air when they respond to an emergency scene?
كيف يقومون حاليا باختبار الهواء حين يستجيبون في حالة طوارئ.
And he kind of comically explained that
وفي نوع من الكوميديا شرح أنه،
time after time, what the firemen would say is:
مرة بعد أخرى رجال الإطفاء سيقولون أنهم،
they would rush to the scene of the crime; they would look around;
سيسرعون إلى مسرح الجريمة. وينظرون حولهم.
if there were no dead policemen, it was OK to go.
إن لم يكن هناك رجال شرطة ميتون، فإنه بإمكانهم الإستمرار.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I mean, this is a true story. They're using policemen as canaries.
أقصد، هذه قصة واقعية. إنهم يستعملون رجال الشرطة ككناريات.
But more seriously, they determined that you could develop
لكن بجدية أكثر، قرروا أنه يمكنهم تطوير
a device that can smell better than the humans,
جهاز يستطيع الشم أحسن من البشر،
and say if it's safe for the firemen.
ويحدد ما إذا كان آمنا لرجال الإطفاء.
In addition, he's spun off a company from the University called ChemSensing,
إضافة إلى ذلك، قد أنشأ شركة من الجامعة سميت ChemSensing،
where they're working on medical equipment.
حيث يشتغلون على معدات طبية
So, a patient can come in and actually blow into their device.
بحيث أن المرضى يمكنهم القدوم والنفخ في آلتهم.
By detecting the odor of particular bacteria, or viruses,
وبالكشف عن رائحة باكتيريا معينة، أو فيروس،
or even lung cancer, the dots will change and they can use
أو حتى سرطان الرئة، ستتغير النقاط ويمكنهم استعمال
software to analyze the results.
برنامج حاسوب لتحليل النتائج.
This can radically improve the way that doctors diagnose patients.
هذا في إمكانه أن يحسن جذريا الطريقة التي يشخص بها الأطباء المرضى.
Currently, they're using a method of trial and error,
حاليا، يستخدمون أسلوب التجربة والخطأ،
but this could tell you precisely what disease you have.
لكن هذا يمكن أن يحدد بدقة أي مرض لديك.
KS: So that was the six we had for you today, but I hope you're starting to see
ك.ش: إذن تلك كانت التقانات الستة التي كانت لدينا لكم اليوم، لكن آمل أنكم بدأتم ترون
why we find these things so fascinating.
لماذا نجد هذه الأشياء مذهلة.
Because every one of these six changed our understanding
لأن كل واحدة من هذه الستة، غيرت فهمنا
of what was possible in the world. Prior to seeing this,
لما كان ممكنا في العالم. قبل رؤية هذه،
we would have assumed: a 10-foot pole couldn't fit in your pocket;
كنا لنفترض أن عصا بطول 10 أقدام لا يمكنها أن تلائم جيبكم.
something as inexpensive as ink couldn't sense the way paper is being bent;
شيئ رخيص كالحبر لا يمكنه أن يشعر بالطريقة التي طوي بها الورق.
every one of these things -- and we're constantly trying to find more.
كل واحد من هذه الأشياء. ونحن نحاول باستمرار إيجاد المزيد.
ZK: This is something that Keith and I really enjoy doing.
ز.ك: هذا شيء نستمتع أنا وكيث فعلا بالقيام به.
I'm sure it's obvious to you now, but it was actually yesterday
أنا متأكد أنه واضح لكم الآن، لكن في الواقع البارحة
that I was reminded of why. I was having a conversation
تم تذكيري لماذا. كنت أجري محادثة
with Steve Jurvetson, over downstairs by the escalators,
مع ستيف جيرفيتسون بالقرب من الدور السفلي من جانب السلالم المتحركة،
and he was telling me that when Chris sent out that little box,
وكان يخبرني أنه حين أرسل إليه كريس ذلك الصندوق الصغير،
one of the items in it was the hydrophobic sand --
أحد العناصر فيه كان الرمل الكاره للماء --
the sand that doesn't get wet. He said that he was playing with it with his son.
الرمل الذي لا يبتل. قال بأنه كان يلعب به مع ابنه.
And you know, his son was mesmerized,
وتعرفون، ابنه كان مفتونا،
because he would dunk it in the water, he would take it out
لأنه بإمكانه غمره في الماء، وإخراجه
and it was bone dry. A few weeks later, he said that his son
وهو جاف تماما. بضعة أسابيع لاحقة، قال، أن ابنه
was playing with a lock of his mother's hair, and he noticed
كان يلعب بخصلة من شعر أمه، ولاحظ
that there were some drops of water on the hair.
أن هناك بضعة قطرات ماء على الشعرة.
And he took the thing and he looked up to Steve and he said,
وأخذها ونظر إلى ستيف وقال،
"Look, hydrophobic string."
"انظر، وتر كاره للماء."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I mean, after hearing that story -- that really summed it up for me.
أعني، بعد سماع تلك القصة، ذلك بالفعل قد لخص الأمر لي.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
KS: Thank you.
ك.ش: شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)